Rizqy Amelia Zein

Curriculum Vitae

Assistant Professor
Department of Psychology
Universitas Airlangga

Kampus B UNAIR Jalan Airlangga 4-6 Surabaya

Jawa Timur, Indonesia 60286

Email: amelia.zein@psikologi.unair.ac.id

Web: http://rameliaz.github.io Codes: http://github.com/rameliaz

Introduction

My PhD project focuses on investigating the mental conceptualization of science-religion relationship through the lens of moral cognition perspectives. I'm broadly interested in researching health misinformation, conspiracy beliefs, and public attitudes to science. I'm also very passionate about research methods, meta-research, computational reproducibility, psychometrics, and latent variable modeling.

Academic Positions

| 2018 – | Assistant Professor (Tenured Civil Servant) | Universitas Airlangga |
|-------------|--|-----------------------|
| 2015 – 2018 | Assistant Professor (Probationary Civil Servant) | Universitas Airlangga |
| 2011 – 2015 | Temporary Tutor | Universitas Airlangga |

Education

| 2021 – | PhD in Social Psychology (Dr. phil.), Fakultäten für | Ludwig Maxmillian Universität, |
|-------------|--|----------------------------------|
| | Psychologie und Pädagogik | München, Germany |
| 2012 – 2013 | Master of Science (M.Sc.) in Social Research | University of Edinburgh, United |
| | School of Social and Political Science | Kingdom |
| 2007 – 2011 | Sarjana Psikologi (S.Psi.) (GPA: 3.65/4.00) | Universitas Airlangga, Surabaya, |
| | Faculty of Psychology | Indonesia |

Awards, Honors, and Scholarship

| 2021 | Deutscher Akademischer Austauschdienst (DAAD), Programm Forschungsstipendien - |
|------|--|
| | Promotionen in Deutschland |
| 2018 | Dean Award of Teaching Excellence |
| 2017 | Dean Award of Teaching Excellence |
| 2016 | Dean Award of Teaching Excellence |
| 2012 | Unggulan Scholarship, Indonesian Ministry of Education and Culture |
| 2011 | Awarded cum laude and distinction at undergraduate graduation |
| 2010 | Singgih Dirga Gunarsa Award (3rd place) |

Grants

| 2021 | Travel | Attending Aspen Global Congress on Scientific Thinking and Action, The Aspen |
|------|----------|--|
| | | Institute Science and Society Program, Rome, 17-20 March 2021. |
| 2020 | Research | Data Collection Grant; Institute for Future Studies (IFFS) Sweden. International |

| | | Study of Norms Violations during Coronavirus Pandemic. Role: Research |
|------|----------|---|
| | | Collaborator. |
| 2020 | Research | 42/UN3.1.9/2020; Universitas Airlangga ECR Grant. <i>Health Misinformation, Vaccine Hesitancy, and Religiosity: A Meta-Analysis Study.</i> Role: Collaborator. |
| 2019 | Travel | Attending Triangle Scholarly Communication Institute (TriangleSCI), Durham (NC), 13-17 October 2019. |
| 2019 | Travel | Attending SIPS Pre-Conference RepliCATS workshop, Rotterdam, 6-7 July 2019 |
| 2019 | Research | Data Collection Grant; Institute for Future Studies (IFFS) Sweden. <i>International Study of Meta-Norms</i> . Role: Research Collaborator. |
| 2018 | Research | 886/UN3/2018; Universitas Airlangga ECR Grant. <i>Protecting those who care:</i> Comparing subjective and actual risk of contracting lung TB in healthcare workers. |
| | | Role: PI |
| 2017 | Research | 39/UN3.1.9/2017; Faculty of Psychology Universitas Airlangga ECR Grant. <i>Do justice and trust matter to supporting social health insurance policy?</i> Role: PI |

Scientific Contributions

Peer-reviewed journal articles

- 1. **Zein, R.A.**, Wulandari, R.D., Ridlo, I.A., Hendriani, W., Suhariadi, F., & Rianto, A. (2022). The characteristics of occupational Tuberculosis risk in health care workers. *International Journal of Health Planning and Management*. Early view. https://doi.org/10.1002/hpm.3489
- 2. **Zein, R. A.**, Putri, N. K., & Ridlo, I. A. (2020). Do justice and trust affect acceptability of Indonesian social health insurance policy? *International Journal of Health Governance*, *25*(1), 78-92. https://doi.org/10.1108/IJHG-05-2019-0028
- 3. **Zein, R. A.** (2018). 'Is Ethnicity the Root of all Evil?' Engaging Macro and Micro Analysis of Ethnic Violence in Post New-order Indonesia. *Politik Indonesia: Indonesian Political Science Review*, 3(2), 262–279. https://doi.org/10.15294/ipsr.v3i2.13985
- 4. **Zein, R. A.**, & Alfian, I. N. (2018). Faktor Determinan Perilaku Konservasi Energi dalam Skala Rumah Tangga dan Sektor Transportasi pada Konsumen Produk Elektronik Ramah Lingkungan dan BBM Non-Subsidi. *Jurnal Psikologi*, 45(3), 231. https://doi.org/10.22146/jpsi.10818
- 5. **Zein, R. A.** (2018). What's the matter with being Indonesian? A social representation approach to unravelling Indonesian national identity / ¿Qué significa ser indonesio? Una perspectiva de la representación social para desentrañar la identidad nacional indonesia. *Revista de Psicologia Social*, 33(2), 390–423. https://doi.org/10.1080/02134748.2018.1435219
- 6. **Zein, R. A.**, Suhariadi, F., & Hendriani, W. (2017). Estimating the effect of lay knowledge and prior contact with pulmonary TB patients, on health-belief model in a high-risk pulmonary TB transmission population. *Psychology Research and Behavior Management*, *Volume 10*, 187–194. https://doi.org/10.2147/PRBM.S134034

Collaborations

- 1. Bago, B., [...], **Zein, R.A.**, [...], Hoekstra, R., & Aczel, B. (2022). Situational factors shape moral judgements in the trolley dilemma in Eastern, Southern and Western countries in a culturally diverse sample. *Nature Human Behaviour*. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-022-01319-5
- 2. McLamore, Q., [...], **Zein, R.A.**, [...], Yeung, W.L.V., & Burrows, B. (2022). Trust in scientific information mediates associations between conservatism and coronavirus responses in the U.S., but few other nations. *Scientific Reports*, *12*, 3724. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-07508-6

- 3. Eriksson, K., [...], **Zein, R.A.**, [...], Zirganou-Kazolea, L., & Van Lange, P. (2021). Perceptions of the appropriate response to norm violation in 57 societies. *Nature Communication*, *12*(1), 1-11. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-021-21602-9
- 4. Irawan, D. E., Abraham, J., **Zein, R. A.**, Ridlo, I. A., & Aribowo, E. K. (2021). Open access in Indonesia. *Development and Change*, *52*, 651-660. https://doi.org/10.1111/dech.12637
- 5. Maison, D., Marchlewska, M., **Zein, R. A.**, Syarifah, D., & Purba, H. (2019). Religiously permissible consumption: The influence of the halal label on product perceptions depending on the centrality of religiosity. *Journal of Islamic Marketing*, *10*(3), 948–960. https://doi.org/10.1108/JIMA-07-2018-0119
- Ridlo, I. A., & Zein, R. A. (2018b). #CondomEmoji: Are urban Indonesians receptive to a social media-based campaign for safer sex? *Health Education*, 118(5), 386–401. https://doi.org/10.1108/HE-02-2018-0010
- 7. Ridlo, I. A., & **Zein, R. A.** (2018a). Arah Kebijakan Kesehatan Mental: Tren Global dan Nasional Serta Tantangan Aktual. *Buletin Penelitian Kesehatan*, 46(1), 45–52. https://doi.org/10.22435/bpk.v46i1.56
- 8. Maison, D., Marchlewska, M., Syarifah, D., **Zein, R. A.**, & Purba, H. P. (2018). Explicit versus implicit "Halal" information: Influence of the halal label and the country-of-origin information on product perceptions in Indonesia. *Frontiers in Psychology*, *9*(MAR), 1–7. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2018.00382
- 9. Dewi, T. K., & **Zein, R. A.** (2017). Predicting Intention to Perform Breast Self-Examination: Application of the Theory of Reasoned Action. *Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention*, 11. https://doi.org/10.22034/APJCP.2017.18.11.2945
- Fajrianthi, F., & Zein, R. A. (2017). Development of a psychological test to measure ability-based emotional intelligence in the Indonesian workplace using an item response theory. *Psychology Research and Behavior Management, Volume 10*, 339–352. https://doi.org/10.2147/PRBM.S143113
- Suhariadi, F., Zein, R. A., Alfian, I. N., & Hadi, C. (2016). The Tale of Seeking Treatment: A
 Qualitative Study of Pulmonary Tuberculosis Patients. Psychology, Community & Health, 5(3),
 229–243. https://doi.org/10.5964/pch.v5i3.152

Book Chapter

Zein, R. A. (2021). Metode Penelitian dalam Psikologi Politik. In W. Yustisia, M. A. Hakim, & R. Ardi (Ed.), *Psikologi politik* (pp. 33-74). Jakarta: Penerbit Buku Kompas.

Preprints and prepared manuscripts

- **Zein, R. A.**, Arinda, M. F., Rikardi, A., Ardelia, V., & Ridlo, I.A. (2020). The enemy of 'ummah: Belief in Jewish conspiracy theories indirectly affected vaccination decisions. *PsyArXiv*. https://doi.org/10.31234/osf.io/53qsk.
- **Zein, R. A.,** Gollwitzer, M., & Dharmaputra, R. (2022). "It all boils down to Jews" Antisemitic conspiracy beliefs predict Indonesians' endorsement for pro-Russian sentiments on the Ukraine war. *Submitted to Social Psychology.*

Selected non-peer-reviewed writings & op-eds

1. **Zein, R.A.** (2021). Open science can help accelerate – and protect – high-quality research in

- low-income countries. The Conversation France.
- 2. **Zein, R.A.** (2021). 27% penduduk Indonesia masih ragu terhadap vaksin COVID-19, mengapa penting meyakinkan mereka. *The Conversation Indonesia*.
- 3. **Zein, R.A.** (2020). Mengapa anjuran "berpikir positif" saat pandemi COVID-19 justru bahayakan nyawa banyak orang. *The Conversation Indonesia*.
- 4. Irawan, D.E., Abraham, J., **Zein, R.A.**, & Gutham, S. (2020). India's plan to pay journal subscription fees for all its citizen may end up making science harder to access. *The Conversation Indonesia*.
- 5. **Zein, R. A.** (2019). Prabowo Tak Percaya Hasil Hitung Cepat: Mengapa partisan berpikir konspiratif? *The Conversation Indonesia*.

Collaborative multi-national projects

- 1. 2022 University of Michigan, United States (US). *Cross-Cultural Disgust Perception Project*. Pl: Joshua Ackerman, Daniel M. T. Fessler, & Thomas Kupfer.
- 2. 2021 University of Sussex, United Kingdom (UK). *The convergent and discriminant validity of maths anxiety and statistics anxiety: A multi-site, multi-study project.* PI: Prof. Andy Field and Jenny Terry (University of Sussex, Brighton, UK).
- 3. 2020 Institute for Future Studies (IFFS) Sweden. *International Study of Norms Violations during Coronavirus Pandemic*. Pl: Dr. Giulia Andrighetto (Institute of Cognitive Sciences and Technology, Italy).
- 2020 Psychological Science Accelerator (PSA). Moral thinking across the world: Exploring the influence of personal force and intention in moral dilemma judgements. [Accepted 1st stage registered report in Nature Human Behavior). Pl: Dr. Balasz Aczel (ELTE University, Hungary).
- University of Massachusetts, Amherst. The persuasiveness of strategic science communication on compliance with scientific recommendations across Nations during the COVID-19 pandemic. PI: Dr. Bernhard Leidner (UMass, Amherst).
- 6. 2019 Institute for Future Studies (IFFS) Sweden. *International Study of Meta-Norms.* PI: Dr. Kimmo Eriksson (University of Stockholm).

Professional Community Services

Ad-hoc peer-review

Journal of Ethnic and Migration Studies (x2), PLoS ONE (x6), Social Justice Research (2x), Psychology and Sexuality (x1), Psychology Research and Behavior Management (x1), Jurnal Berkala Epidemiologi (x1), MAKARA Human Behavior Studies in Asia (x1), Journal of Social Psychology (x3), International Quarterly of Community Health Education (1x).

Others

| 2019 | Committee, 36th Anniversary of Faculty of Psychology |
|--------------|--|
| 2019 | Committee, Webinar Sains – Advancing Science in Indonesia: Current Global Research |
| | Practices |
| 2019-present | Member/Co-Founder, Sains Terbuka Airlangga (https://sainsterbukaua.github.io/) |
| 2019-present | Researcher-in-training, Institute for Globally Distributed Open Research and Education |
| | (IGDORE) |
| 2019-2020 | Volunteer, INArxiv pre-print server |

Presentations

Invited talks

| 12/10/2022 | Perkembangan Kajian Psikologi Moral Secara Global dan di Indonesia, Fakultas Psikologi Universitas Muhammadiyah Prof. Dr. HAMKA dan Ikatan Psikologi Sosial |
|------------|--|
| 01/10/2022 | Menulis Pembahasan dan Abstrak dalam Artikel Ilmiah, Pusat Kajian Psikologi Komunikasi dan Budaya (PUSKALOKA) dan SUKSMA: Jurnal Psikologi Universitas Sanata Dharma Yogyakarta |
| 14/09/2022 | Internasionalisasi, Pemeringkatan, dan Integritas Akademik di Universitas, Fakultas Keguruan dan Ilmu Pendidikan (FKIP) Universitas Muhammadiyah Prof. Dr. HAMKA |
| 27/08/2020 | Mengelola Pembelajaran Jarak-Jauh dengan Online Delivery , Fakultas Psikologi Universitas Airlangga |
| 08/08/2020 | Penolakan Vaksin, Kepercayaan Konspiratif, dan Bagaimana Menyikapinya, Webinar Series: Ilmuwan Merespon Pandemi, <i>Society of Indonesian Science Journalists</i> (SISJ) & Akademi Ilmuwan Muda Indonesia (ALMI) |
| 05/04/2020 | Sintesis Pengetahuan dengan Meninjau Literatur, Department of Health Policy and Administration Universitas Airlangga |
| 21/09/2019 | Menulis Artikel Opini dan Komunikasi Sains, Kelas Literasi Klub Seri Buku |
| 08/08/2019 | Menulis Artikel Populer dari Karya Ilmiah, Direktorat Sistem Informasi (DSI) Universitas Airlangga |
| 07/23/2019 | Self-Archiving, The Conversation Indonesia Writing Workshop |
| 19/07/2019 | Self-Archiving and Introduction to Open Science , The Indonesian Journal of Health Administration Workshop |
| 25/04/2019 | Encouraging Academics to Embrace #OpenScience, The 5th UGM Public Health Symposium |
| 21/01/2019 | Challenging Religious Extremism: Social Psychology Perspective, Universitas Nahdlatul 'Ulama Surabaya |

Workshops

| 30/01/2020 | Confirmatory Factor Analysis, Faculty of Education Universitas Negeri Semarang |
|---------------|---|
| 22-23/11/2019 | Multigroup Structural Equation Modeling, Faculty of Psychology Universitas Airlangga |
| 02/11/2019 | Multilevel Modeling/Linear Mixed Effect, Faculty of Psychology Universitas Islam Sultan |
| | Agung, Semarang |
| 04/09/2019 | Multilevel Modeling/Linear Mixed Effect, Faculty of Psychology Universitas Airlangga |
| 05/10/2018 | Statistical Power Workshop, Faculty of Psychology Universitas Airlangga |

Professional Development

Workshops

| Good Clinical Practice, NDA Clinical Trials Network |
|--|
| Multilevel Modeling, Indonesian Association of Social Psychology (IPS) |
| Psychological Test Adaptation, HIMPSI Jawa Timur |
| Basic and Advanced Training on Bioethics, Faculty of Public Health Universitas |
| Airlangga |
| Applied Approach, Universitas Airlangga |
| PEKERTI, Universitas Airlangga |
| Pelatihan Dasar Calon PNS Golongan III, Pusdiklat Kementerian Pendidikan dan |
| Kebudayaan |
| |

MOOCs

| 23/10/2019 | Improving your statistical questions, TU Eindhoven, Coursera |
|------------|---|
| 01/02/2019 | Improving your statistical inferences, TU Eindhoven, Coursera |
| 03/04/2018 | Inferential statistics University of Amsterdam Coursera |

Summer School

07/03/2013 Advanced Issues in Survey Design and Analysis, Utrecht University

Professional Membership

| 2020-present | Society of Indonesian Science Journalists (SISJ) |
|--------------|--|
| 2019-present | Society for the Improvement of Psychological Sciences (SIPS) |
| 2017-present | International Society of Political Psychology (ISPP) |
| 2013-present | Indonesian Association of Social Psychology (IPS) |

Skills

Language

| Native | Bahasa Jawa |
|--------|--|
| Native | Bahasa Indonesia |
| C1 | English, IELTS 7.5 (2020, Listening 8.0, Reading 8.5, Writing 6.5, & Speaking 7.5) |
| A2 | German |
| A1 | Japanese |

Methodology/Statistics

Latent Variable Modeling
Latent Response Model
Multilevel Modeling/Linear Mixed Effect
General Linear Models
Generalised Linear Models
Systematic Review
Meta-Analysis
Directed Acyclic Graphs (DAG)
Network Analysis
Lab.js
Sosci Survey, SurveyMonkey, LimeSurvey, Qualtrics, & formr

Programming

R HTML PHP

Mentorship

| 2021 | Riezky Putra Santoso, undergraduate thesis |
|------|--|
| 2021 | Faza Izzudin Nuha, undergraduate thesis |

| 2021 | Fiona Fira Winata, undergraduate thesis |
|------|--|
| 2020 | Naufal A. Farisy, undergraduate thesis |
| 2020 | Sita Nadia Salsabilla Widodo, undergraduate thesis |
| 2020 | Hibatullah Anfal Farisi, undergraduate thesis |
| 2020 | Maghfira Fahmi Arinda, undergraduate thesis |
| 2020 | Audi Ahmad Rikardi, undergraduate thesis |

Teaching

Odd Semester PSK301 Community Mental Health

2020/2021 PSA212 Community Assessment and Intervention

PSU108 Personality Psychology (Regular Programme)

PSU108 Personality Psychology (IUP/AMERTA)

PHP101 Philosophy of Science (IUP) PSS405 Social Psychology Seminar

Even Semester PNP206 Quantitative Research Methods and Data Analysis

2020/2021 PSS104 Social Cognition (Regular Programme) PSS104 Social Cognition (IUP/AMERTA)

PNP206 Quantitative Research Methods (Master of Professional Psychology)

MAS702 Advanced Statistics (Master of Professional Psychology)

PSS405 Social Psychology Seminar

For assigned courses from 2020 backwards, please refer to PDDikti database.

Last updated: 07 Oktober 2022
http://rameliaz.github.io/files/cv